American Academy in Rome
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Board of Trustees Records, 1897-1957, undated, Series 2:; (box 1-17; 15.32 linear ft.)
  - Records of Officers, 1897-1957, undated, 2.3:
    - Presidents, 1898-1957, undated, 2.3.1:
      - James Kellum Smith (Box 6, Reel 5758)
        - Fellowship in Architecture/Cash Prize in Architecture, 1938-1942 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (includes thoughts on fellowship competition and its regulations, suggestions for jury members, and letters of recommendation)
        - Finance Committee, 1938-1953 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
        - Fraser, Leon (Treasurer), 1939-1944 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
        - Fulbright Bill, 1946 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
        - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1938-1945 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (routine business; also, correspondence about fellowship juries and competitions, investments, and fellows)
        - Invitations, 1938-1947 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (regarding sending delegates to inaugural and ceremonial functions)
        - James, Henry (Vice President; Acting President), 1945 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (correspondence with State Department regarding acting director Morey and the Office of War Information's use of academy facilities, finances, James's resignation)
        - Lamond, Felix, (Professor of Music), 1939-1940 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
        - Library, 1943-1946 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (includes correspondence regarding the of hiring a new librarian)
        - McClellan, George B. (Vice President), 1938-1939 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
        - Moore, Lamont (Assistant Director, Rome), 1948 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (letter requesting Moore to see about maintenance of Mead's grave in the Rome Cemetery)
        - Morey, Charles R. (Acting Director, Rome), 1945-1949 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (routine administrative matters; letters concerning finances, staff, and renting Villa Chiaraviglio for embassy use)
        - Nominating Committee, 1945-1947 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
        - Pratt, Richardson (Secretary), 1946-1947 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
        - Richardson, Ethel, 1947-1952 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (concerns property adjoining American Academy in Rome [subsequently acquired in 1963])
        - Roberts, Laurance P. (Director, Rome), 1946-1957 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (routine administrative matters; also includes conditions of appointment, reports on director's activities, fellows and staff, summer school, housing, Richardson villa, finances and budget, annual exhibitions)
        - Sowerby, Leo, 1946 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
        - State Department, 1941-1946 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (mainly concerns efforts to transfer U.S. funds to academy during wartime)
        - Stevens, Gorham Phillips (former Director, Rome), 1947-1951 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (includes copies of his recent articles and proposed bequest to academy)
        - Stuart, Meriwether (Executive Secretary Pro Tem), 1946; 1949 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (includes proposal for 50th anniversary publication)
        - Trustees, undated, 1938-1957 (Box 6, Reel 5759)
          (correspondence with individual trustees; includes observations on the method for selecting architectural fellows, burglaries at academy, appointment of acting director Morey, library, nominations and elections)
        - Vatican Payments, 1946 (Box 6, Reel 5760)
          (thanks and repayment for funds advanced to academy staff during World War II when money could not be transferred from the U.S. to Italy)
        - Villa Aurelia, circa 1907 (Box 6, Reel 5760)
          (received by Smith, 1940; notes and background information compiled by Charles W. Leavitt (via Mrs. Frank Miles Day))
        - Walker, John III (Associate in Charge, School of Fine Arts, Rome), 1939 (Box 6, Reel 5760)
        - Williams, Mary T. (Executive Secretary), 1947-1955 (Box 6, Reel 5760)
    - Vice Presidents, 1905-1943, 2.3.2:
      A paucity of vice presidential records, a total of 31 items for three individuals - Theodore N. Ely, George B. McClellan, and Henry James - suggests that these items probably were attachments to others' letters that somehow became separated.
      Records are arranged chronologically by vice president.
      - Theodore N. Ely, Correspondence, 1905-1911 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        (concerning incorporation and Villa Mirafiore)
      - George B. McClellan, Correspondence, 1926-1938 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        (library, finances, reducing expenses, report of interview with director Hewlett, letters from director Aldrich with news of staff and fellows)
      - Henry James, Correspondence, 1945 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        (regarding acting director Dinsmoor's passport problems, State Department's request to lease academy housing for temporary use by embassy staff, contract for educational services to U.S. Army; letter from Director Morey detailing use of academy facilities and staff by U.S. Information Service, embassy and army)
    - Secretaries, 1898-1947, undated, 2.3.3:
      Files of secretaries Frank D. Millet (1.9 linear feet) and his successor C. Grant La Farge (2.0 linear feet) contain no obvious gaps. Millet's files include scattered correspondence of assistant W. R. Wolfe; the content of La Farge's records shifts after 1919, with the advent of an executive secretary in the New York office who tended to the more routine administrative matters (see Series 3). La Farge's files include the correspondence of assistant secretaries W. R. Wolfe and Frank B. Rowell. Records of earlier and later secretaries, H. Siddons Mowbray, William B. Dinsmoor, and H. Richardson Pratt, are very sparse with only a few folders for Mowbray and Pratt and, in Dinsmoor's case, three items.
      Records are arranged chronologically by secretary with the names of the secretary at the top of each file group indicated in bold type. Within the file group for each secretary, general correspondence files are followed by other files arranged alphabetically by subject or by name of the person to whom the file relates.
      - H. Siddons Mowbray (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - Ballots and Proxies, 1879-1900 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - Correspondence, undated, 1898-1900 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
          (includes letters about academy buildings, fellows, exhibitions,)
        - Invoices, (for engraving and printing) 1899-1903 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
      - Frank D. Millet (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - General Correspondence, undated, 1904-1912 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - American Institute of Architects, undated, 1905-1911 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - Barney, Charles T. (Treasurer), 1905-1909 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - Blashfield, Edwin H. (Trustee), 1904-1912 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
          (mainly routine business; also, letters about library, fellows, relations between archaeologists and artists, endorsement of Millet for director)
        - Boring, William A. (Treasurer), 1909-1912 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - Breck, George W. (Director, Rome), 1905-1910 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
          (includes descriptions of academy properties, possible acquisitions, inventory of Villa Mirafiore furnishings; letters summarizing activities of director, staff, and fellows; endowment fund, negotiations with J. P. Morgan, Sr., expenses, exhibitions, visitors, bibliography of prescribed reading for architects, appointment of director Crowninshield)
        - Burnham, Daniel H. (Trustee), undated, 1905-1911 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
          (includes letters regarding Endowment Fund, resignation)
        - Carter, Jesse Benedict (Director, American School of Classical Studies in Rome), 1909-1912 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - Crowninshield, Frederic (Trustee; Director, Rome), undated, 1907-1911 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
          (regarding visitors, fellows, endowment fund, bequest of Villa Aurelia, exhibitions, consolidation with American School of Classical Studies in Rome, Janiculum land purchases by J. P. Morgan, Sr.)
        - Day, Frank Miles (Trustee; Chairman, Executive Committee; Acting President), 1905-1912 (Box 7, Reel 5760)
        - Ely, Theodore N. (Vice President), undated, 1904-1912 (Box 7, Reel 5760-5761)
          (includes letters about endowment fund, Villa Mirafiore, executive committee business, Villa Aurelia)
        - Endowment, undated, 1905-1912 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (mainly correspondence with and about individual and institutional subscribers to endowment fund and McKim column; also, letters of solicitation, lists of donors)
        - Fellowship in Architecture--Applicants, A-Z, 1910 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (requests for general information; letters of application and recommendation)
        - Fellowship in Architecture--Competition, 1909-1911 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (includes regulations and statements of competition problems; also, correspondence with jurors and participating schools of architecture)
        - Fellowship in Architecture--Recipients, 1907-1910 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (correspondence with or about Harry E. Warren (1907), Ernest F. Lewis (1908) and Richard H. Smythe (1910))
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts, 1908 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (notes and report of committee to nominate students for fellowships)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Applicants, A-Z (painters), 1909-1910 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (letters of application, correspondence with institutions supervising preliminary competition, and invitations to final competition)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Painting Competition, 1909-1910 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (includes committee reports and correspondence, correspondence with participating schools, preliminary and final problems, regulations)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Paris Competition, 1911 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (correspondence with Paris Society of Painters about conducting a Rome Prize competition in Paris)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Recipients, 1907-1910 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (correspondence with or about Barry Faulkner (1907), C.Y. Harvey (1907), Sherry E. Fry (1908), Frank P. Fairbanks (1909), Paul Manship (1909), Albin Polasek (1910), and Henry Lawrence Wolfe (1910))
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Sculpture Competition, 1906, 1909-1911 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
          (includes letters of inquiry, correspondence with committee, letters of application, preliminary competition problems, correspondence with participating schools, invitations to final competition)
        - French, Daniel C. (Trustee), 1905-1912 (Box 7, Reel 5761)
        - Incorporation of American Academy in Rome, 1905 (Box 8, Reel 5761)
          (includes correspondence with Congressmen, and copy of proposed Act S.7438)
        - Incorporation of American Academy in Rome--Celebratory Dinner [March 25], 1905 (Box 8, Reel 5761)
          (list of acceptances, correspondence A-Z, text of remarks by McKim)
        - Landi, Claude P. (Secretary, Rome), 1910 (Box 8, Reel 5761)
        - Laurie, Charles (Secretary, Rome), 1911-1912 (Box 8, Reel 5761)
          (includes letters about fellow Lawrence Wolfe's disappearance, suggestions for financial management)
        - Life Membership Acknowledgments, A-Z, 1905 (Box 8, Reel 5761)
        - McKim, Charles F. (President), 1904-1909 (Box 8, Reel 5761)
          (routine administrative correspondence; also, resolutions on the death of McKim, letter to his daughter)
        - Mead, William R. (Treasurer; President), undated, 1904-1912 (Box 8, Reel 5761-5762)
          (includes correspondence regarding endowment fund subscriptions, Villa Aurelia, "Memoranda of Mr. Mead's Visit to Rome," consolidation with the American School of Classical Studies in Rome, fellows and staff, finances, J. P. Morgan, Sr., reports from Millet in Rome, Crowninshield's resignation, ideas about new director, Carter's and Stevens's roles and expectations, married students)
        - Morgan, J. Pierpont, Sr. (Trustee) 1906-1911 (Box 8, Reel 5762)
          (includes letters about Villa Aurelia)
        - Mowbray, H. Siddons (Treasurer; Trustee; Director, Rome), 1904-1911 (Box 8, Reel 5762)
          (includes letters about Villa Aurora)
        - Pine, John B. (Trustee; Legal Counsel), 1910-1912 (Box 8, Reel 5762)
          (includes letters concerning revision of constitution and by-laws, appointment of Millet as director)
        - Shipment of Students' Work, 1903-1904 (Box 8, Reel 5762)
        - Stevens, Gorham Phillips (Director, Rome), 1912 (Box 8, Reel 5762)
          (includes discussion of titles, activities of staff and fellows, reducing expenses, Villa Aurelia)
        - Trustees, undated, 1904-1912 (Box 8, Reel 5762)
          (routine business; also, correspondence with individual trustees includes discussion of endowment fund, appointment of director Crowninshield, fellows, competition regulations, students accepting commissions, Villa Aurelia, amendment of charter, consolidation with the American School of Classical Studies in Rome)
        - Villa Aurelia, 1909-1912 (Box 8, Reel 5762)
          (correspondence concerning Heyland bequest, acceptance, settlement proposal, opinions on the suitability of Villa Aurelia as a home for the academy, legal advice, J. P. Morgan, Sr., financial statements, new building, alterations to Villa Aurelia)
        - Villa Aurelia--Will of Clara J. Heyland and Inventory of Furnishings, 1909-1910 (Box 8, Reel 5762)
        - Villa Mirafiore, 1904-1906, 1911 (Box 8, Reel 5762-5763)
          (correspondence concerning purchase [with 1916 cover letter to William R. Mead indicating that the file should be kept with the secretary's records])
        - Walters, Henry (Trustee; Finance Committee), 1904-1912 (Box 8, Reel 5763)
          (includes correspondence regarding purchase of Villa Mirafiore, Endowment Fund subscription)
        - Wolfe, W. R. (Assistant Secretary), undated, 1909-1912 (Box 8, Reel 5763)
          (letters summarizing daily activities and mail received during Millet's absence) (Note: File was filmed out of order and appears on film after Villa Aurelia)
      - C. Grant La Farge (Box 9, Reel 5763)
        - General Correspondence, undated, 1912-1929 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
        - American School of Classical Studies in Rome, 1912 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (regarding consolidation agreement)
        - Association of the Alumni of the American Academy in Rome, 1915-1919 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (about recommendations for changes in competition regulations)
        - Boring, William A. (Treasurer), undated, 1912-1919 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (mainly routine business; also, includes correspondence concerning Villa Aurelia construction loan from J. P, Morgan, Sr., letters about women competing for fellowships)
        - Carter, Jesse Benedict (Director, Rome), undated, 1912-1917 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (includes letters concerning his title, Stevens's responsibilities, fellows, budget, finances, fundraising, academy properties, outbreak of World War I, housing for staff and students, enlistment of fellows, collaborative problem, director Carter's and Professor Clark's lecture tours, use of academy buildings for war purposes)
        - Carter, Jesse Benedict--Death, 1917-1918 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (correspondence with Mrs. Carter, letters of condolence, account of his death, copy of will)
        - Carter, Jesse Benedict--Dinner, 1912 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (guest lists and correspondence concerning arrangements for dinner in New York honoring the new director)
        - Clark, Charles Upson (Director, School of Classical Studies), undated, 1915-1918 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (letters about his appointment, administrative matters, requests for leaves of absence to lecture)
        - Collaborative Problem, undated, 1912-1920 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (summary of history, details concerning establishment and administration of the prize; collaborative problems, undated, 1916-1917)
        - Curtis, C. Densmore (Professor of Archaeology), 1918-1920 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (includes proposal for excavation at Lanuvio, Italy, with program of work planned for 1919/20)
        - Customs Duty, 1918 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (inventory of shipment of music scores, receipt, and insurance certificate)
        - Ely Loan Fund, 1915-1918 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
        - Ely, Theodore N. (Vice President), 1914-1916 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (includes correspondence about war conditions in Italy)
        - Endowment, 1912-1931 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
        - Fairbanks, Frank P. (Professor of Fine Arts), 1912-1916 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (mainly concerns exhibitions and shipments)
        - Fellows, 1912-1915 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (correspondence with and about fellows, particularly Roy M. Peterson and Kenneth E. Carpenter, also, overpayments to students, proposed changes in regulations, extension of time)
        - Fellowship in Architecture--Applicants, A-Z, 1913-1915 (Box 9, Reel 5763-5764)
          (completed application forms, 1913; completed application forms for canceled Paris competition, 1914; completed application forms, correspondence with applicants and letters of recommendation, 1915)
        - Fellowship in Architecture--Competition, 1912-1913, 1915 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (includes lists of participants, program of competition, invitations to final competition, and announcement of winners)
        - Fellowship in Architecture--Recipients, 1913-1915 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (correspondence with or about recipients: Walter L. Ward, 1913; William J. Hough, 1914; and Philip T. Shutze, 1915)
        - Fellowship in Classical Studies--Applicants, A-Z, 1914 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (completed application forms)
        - Fellowship in Classical Studies--Recipients, 1914, 1916-1917 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (correspondence with or about recipients: C. Dinsmore Curtis, Eugene S. McCartney, and Horace W. Wright, 1914; John T. Rearson and Gilbert H. Taylor, 1916; Lily Ross Taylor, 1917)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Applicants (painters), A-Z, 1912-1914 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (completed application forms, including correspondence with applicants and letters of recommendation)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Applicants (sculptors), A-Z, 1913 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Painting Competition, 1912-1915 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (includes correspondence with cooperating institutions, administrative details, and program of competition)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Paris Competition, 1913-1914 [1914 canceled] (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (mainly correspondence with Edward P. Mellon planning the competition and announcing the results)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Paris Competition [canceled]--Applicants, A-Z, 1914 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Recipients, 1912-1914, 1916 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (correspondence with or about recipients: Henry Varnum Poor and Eugene F. Savage, 1912; Leo Friedlander, 1913; Harry I. Stickroth, 1914; Allyn Cox and C. Paul Jennewien, 1916)
        - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Sculpture Competition, 1912-1913 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (includes list of cooperating institutions, administrative details, printed circular, and competition problem)
        - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture, undated, 1915-1923 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (correspondence concerning the establishment of fellowships and fundraising for permanent fellowships)
        - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture, Competition, 1914 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (competition rules and procedures)
        - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture--Recipient, 1915 (Box 9, Reel 5763)
          (receipt for fellowship awarded to Edward G. Lawson)
        - French, Daniel C. (Trustee), undated, 1912-1931 (Box 10, Reel 5764)
          (includes letter about gift of F. D. Millet's art books and costumes to the academy, comments on sculptor fellows, "Study in Rome. Preliminary Information and Suggestions for Students in Sculpture, American Academy in Rome")
        - Frick, Henry C., 1905-1912 (Box 10, Reel 5764)
          (regarding Endowment)
        - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1919 (Box 10, Reel 5764)
          (waiver allowing Salvatore Lascari to be appointed a fellow despite being a married man)
        - Hendrickson, G. L. (Professor in Charge, School of Classical Studies), 1913-1919 (Box 10, Reel 5764)
        - Hewlett, J. Monroe (Director, Rome), 1933-1935 (Box 10, Reel 5764)
          (includes comments on financial, educational, and social problems at the academy; also, letters about repairs to Manship fountain, and proposed gifts)
        - Italian Ambassador, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (condolences on the death of director Carter; correspondence concerning Professor Clark's lecture series undertaken on behalf of the Italian government)
        - Janiculum Improvements--Report on Construction Accounts with List of Exhibits A-Q, by Francis W. Kesley, 1915 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
        - Janiculum Improvements--Exhibits A-Q [C, E-H, J-K, and O missing], 1915 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          - A - Contract and Estimates [in Italian]
          - B - Abstract of Main Contract [in English]
          - D - Supplementary Statement of Expenditures [attachment only]
          - I - Description of Architect's Plans
            for New Building, Villa Aurelia, Villa Chiaraviglio, and Villa Bellacci
          - L - Letters of Director Jesse B. Carter
          - L1 Relation of Contracts and Estimates to Ultimate Working Results in the Janiculum Improvement
          - L2 Physical Condition of Villa Aurelia at the Time of Taking Possession
          - L3 Physical Condition of Villa Chiaraviglio
          - L4 Physical Condition of Villa Bellacci
          - L5 Purchase of Water
          - L6 Jessup Loan
          - L7 Insurance on the Academy Property
          - L8 Bank Balance as of February 24, 1915
          - L9 Dismissal of Servant in Connection with Moving - Voucher 702
          - L10 Construction of Women's Building in Villa Aurelia
          - L11 Modification of Banking System in Rome, with Supplementary Letter
          - L12 Commission to Architect
          - L13 Value of Villa Mirafiore as an Asset
          - M - Letters of Gorham P. Stevens
          - M1 Galassi's fee
          - M2 Report on Recent Earthquake
            (effects of war on costs of extra work ordered; cost of lights installed)
          - M3 Earthquake Damage to Villa Aurelia
          - N - Letter of V. Ranieri
            (acknowledging receipt in full for payment of all claims, accompanied by final accounting)
          - P - Vouchers, Classified by Account, through Feb. 22, 1915
          - P1-5 Main Building
          - P6-8 Villa Aurelia
          - P9-11 Villa Chiaraviglio
          - P12-13 Villa Bellacci
          - P14-25 General
          - Q - Vouchers, Classified by Account, Feb. 23-March 13, 1915
          - Q1-3 Main Building
          - Q4 Villa Aurelia
          - Q5-7 Villa Chiaraviglio
          - Q10 General Office
        - Janiculum Plans and Pamphlets, undated, 1910 and 1912 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (includes "Bird's Eye View of the Villa Aurelia and adjoining lands on the Janiculum Hill, Rome," plan of site and New Building, "Studio Legale dell' Avv. Gastone del Frate, Relazione Sopra la Villa Aurelia," and illustrated article about Villa Aurelia from The American Institute of Architects Quarterly Bulletin)
        - Thomas Spencer Jerome Trust, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
        - Library, 1913 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (list of donated periodicals)
        - McClellan, George B. (Trustee), 1913 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (letter recounting his visit to the Academy in Rome)
        - Mead, William R. (President), 1912-1925 (Box 10, Reel 5765)